<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Henrique Castro Martins</title>
<link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://henriquemartins.net/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.0.38</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 03:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Investment–cash flow sensitivity and investor protection</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/JBFA_2022/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract"><em>Abstract:</em></h3>
<p>We examine the role of country-level legal investor protection (i.e., shareholder and creditor protection) on firm investment–cash flow sensitivity. Using underexplored research data on investor protection across 21 countries and working with a conservative empirical design, we extend prior literature on the relation between investor protection and investment–cash flow sensitivity and provide new evidence on how these country-level attributes interact to explain a firm’s investment–cash flow sensitivity. We find that either the strong legal protection of minority shareholders or the strong legal protection of creditors reduces the sensitivity of investment to internal cash flow. However, in countries with strong levels of both minority shareholder and creditor protection, investment–cash flow sensitivity increases. Our results remain robust after controlling for several alternative explanations. The results support the argument that overregulation arises when policymakers increase investor protection at levels that lead firms to avoid external sources of finance, hampering firm investment. Our findings suggest that countries face a regulatory trade-off such that increasing investor protection (either shareholder or creditors protection) enhances financial markets efficiency, but excessive regulation can indeed lead to financial markets inefficiencies.</p>
<p>Co-authored with <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Kfg4CwQAAAAJ&amp;hl=pt-BR">Luiz Ricardo Kabbach de Castro</a>, <a href="https://www.hec.ca/en/profs/eduardo.schiehll.html">Eduardo Schiehll</a> and <a href="https://eaesp.fgv.br/en/people/paulo-renato-soares-terra">Paulo Terra</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Governance</category>
  <category>Corporate Finance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/JBFA_2022/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/JBFA_2022/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Integrating uncertainty and governance into a capital structure puzzle: can risk-taking and rule-taking explain zero-leverage firms?</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/RMS_2022/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.1007/s11846-021-00500-w" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">Integrating uncertainty and governance into a capital structure puzzle: can risk-taking and rule-taking explain zero-leverage firms?</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract"><em>Abstract:</em></h3>
<p>This study uses a multidisciplinary lens to investigate new determinants of the puzzling phenomenon of zero leverage, where firms contain only equity in their capital structure. We draw on insights from entrepreneurship and creativity theories, alongside traditional corporate governance (CG) literature, to reframe the construct of risk-taking and develop the novel construct of rule-taking, which entails compliance with powerful outside parties and current best practices of CG. We hypothesize that risk-taking is associated with a wider wedge of information and costs regarding internal and external financing, leading to a greater likelihood of debt eschewing. Conversely, rule-taking is hypothesized to reduce the range of acceptable choices in the firm, which makes the adoption of the “aberrant” behavior of zero-leverage less likely. Using 9222 firm-observations from 37 countries, the results corroborate our hypotheses, showing a positive (negative) association between risk-taking (rule-taking) and zero leverage. The results are robust to several alternative specifications and matching samples. Our study offers insights to policymakers and investors to clarify the antecedents of zero-leverage behavior as a strategy to deal with the information gap between insiders and outsiders. Our perspective underscores the existence of an inherent communication penalty between an insider and an outsider when the former is performing actions that are non-typical under the oversight of the latter. Thus, by deepening understanding on risk-taking and rule-taking, we provide a more nuanced view of how firms can optimize capital and CG structures, with special implications for the adoption of well-tailored bundles of CG mechanisms under different circumstances.</p>
<p>Article co-authored with <a href="https://scholar.google.com.br/citations?user=Q7O4il0AAAAJ&amp;hl=pt-BR">Michael Araki</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Governance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/RMS_2022/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/RMS_2022/featured.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Accounting Discretion</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/accounting_discretion/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="accounting-discretion-around-the-world-what-are-the-outcomes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="accounting-discretion-around-the-world-what-are-the-outcomes">Accounting discretion around the world: what are the outcomes?</h3>
<p>Previous corporate governance literature suggests that investors and regulators fear possible opportunistic behaviors coming from managerial discretion; thus, mechanisms (such as governance mechanisms and legal rules) are placed to reduce their discretion. This literature usually defines managerial discretion as the latitude of action allowed to managers and uses firm-level configurations (such as low levels of leverage or ownership concentration) to proxy for it. In this manuscript, we propose a different form of discretion coming from accounting rules, which we name as accounting discretion. Specifically, we investigate systematic differences in accounting that are linked with or provide discretion to managers in 52 countries. We use local accounting rules to assess accounting discretion and to build an index measuring the level of accounting discretion allowed in each country. Our accounting discretion index suggests there is significant variability across the 52 countries in our sample. We argue that understanding country-level variability in accounting discretion is crucial to understand overall managerial discretion at the firm-level. We contribute to the literature by providing an objective measure of accounting discretion across different countries.</p>
<p>Co-authored with <a href="http://lattes.cnpq.br/1670868214172308">Marcio Pimenta</a> (PhD Candidate).</p>
<p>The first article of this project was accepted for presentation at the 6th annual International Corporate Governance Society (<a href="https://icgsociety.org/">ICGS</a>) conference to be held November 14 - 16, 2020.</p>
<p>You can check the slides <a href="https://henriquemartins.net/slideslist/2020-11-14-icgs-presentation/">here</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Governance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/accounting_discretion/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/accounting_discretion/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Competition and ESG practices in emerging markets - Evidence from a difference-in-differences model</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/FRL_2022/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.1016%2Fj.frl.2021.102371" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">Competition and ESG practices in emerging markets: Evidence from a difference-in-differences model</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract"><em>Abstract:</em></h3>
<p>This paper investigates how competition affects firms’ environmental, social, and governance (ESG) practices in 22 emerging markets, using a sample of 6,906 firm-year observations from 2011 to 2019. Using a difference-in-differences technique and matched samples with a treated and a control group, I explore exogenous variation in the competitive environment of one country, Brazil, to assess the competition?s causal effect on ESG. The results suggest that firms adjust ESG practices negatively after a shock in competition, contrasting with previous results from developed economies.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Finance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/FRL_2022/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/FRL_2022/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Blockholders and firm value: Evidence from Brazil</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/RBFIN_2022/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.12660%2Frbfin.v20n2.2022.83645" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">Blockholders and firm value: Evidence from Brazil</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract"><em>Abstract:</em></h3>
<p>This research analyzes the relationship between the presence of blockholders and the value of Brazilian firms. Our analysis comprises all non-financial listed firms in Brazil with data available in the period 2010-2019 (i.e., 1,091 firm-year observations). We estimate Ordinary Least Squares (OLS) models with firm fixed effects and use Propensity Score Matching (PSM) to pair sub-samples and mitigate selection bias concerns. Our results suggest a negative association between Tobin’s Q and the presence of blockholders. Our findings contradict previous studies using samples of international firms but corroborate previous studies using Brazilian firms. We also find that companies with blockholders of the family-type have Tobin’s Q lower than the other types.</p>
<p>Article co-authored with <a href="http://lattes.cnpq.br/4187009689404563">Bruno Brasil Lombello</a> and <a href="http://lattes.cnpq.br/5042677509706552">Marcelo Cabús Klotzle</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Governance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/RBFIN_2022/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/RBFIN_2022/featured.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="60" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Risk taking ang Corporate Governance</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/risk_taking/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="risk-taking-ang-corporate-governance" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="risk-taking-ang-corporate-governance">Risk taking ang Corporate Governance</h3>
<p>Corporate governance research makes claims about the nature of ‘ideal’ arrangements using Agency Theory. However, traditional corporate governance mechanisms designed to curb agency problems may undermine firm growth because they are mostly backward-looking and inherently problematic when facing uncertainty. In fact, they may restrain or disincentivize managerial creativeness and alertness, which can be instrumental to maximize firm value. Our goal is to advance a conceptual framework that integrates into corporate governance elements literature factors that are key for creativity but which have been overlooked in corporate governance. Drawing on a combination of creativity and entrepreneurship literatures, we discuss two parameters—unlikelihood and opacity—which serve as the basis to propose four different types of entrepreneurial projects. Additionally, we provide an in-depth analysis of the optimal corporate governance configurations for each project types. Our framework can inform the design of better tailored governance mechanisms that are specific to a firm’s environment and its projects.</p>
<p>Article co-authored with <a href="https://scholar.google.com.br/citations?user=Q7O4il0AAAAJ&amp;hl=pt-BR">Michael Araki</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Open Science</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/risk_taking/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/risk_taking/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Open Code Community</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/open_science/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="open-code-community" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="open-code-community">Open Code Community</h3>
<p>We are a group of programming and Open Science enthusiasts aiming to share codes for the entire community. Our goal is to help students and professionals with the development of their codes and analyses. If you are willing to contribute to this project, share your code.</p>
<p>If you are looking for research ideas and how to execute them, check the <a href="https://opencodecom.net/">website</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Open Science</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/open_science/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/open_science/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tutorial-Articles - The Importance of Data and Code Sharing</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/RAC_2021/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.1590%2F1982-7849rac2021200212" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">Tutorial-Articles: The Importance of Data and Code Sharing</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract"><em>Abstract:</em></h3>
<p><strong>Context:</strong> this document is designed to be along with those that are in the first edition of the new section of the Journal of Contemporary Administration (RAC): the tutorial-articles section.</p>
<p><strong>Objective:</strong> the purpose is to present the new section and discuss relevant topics of tutorial-articles.</p>
<p><strong>Method:</strong> I divide the document into three main parts. First, I provide a summary of the state of the art in open data and open code at the current date that, jointly, create the context for tutorial-articles. Second, I provide some guidance to the future of the section on tutorial-articles, providing a structure and some insights that can be developed in the future. Third, I offer a short R script to show examples of open data that, I believe, can be used in the future in tutorial-articles, but also in innovative empirical studies.</p>
<p><strong>Conclusion:</strong> finally, I provide a short description of the first tutorial-articles accepted for publication in this current RAC’s edition.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Finance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/RAC_2021/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/RAC_2021/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Does control concentration affect board busyness? International evidence</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/JMG_2020/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.1007%2Fs10997-019-09487-9" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">Does control concentration affect board busyness? International evidence</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract"><em>Abstract:</em></h3>
<p>Previous literature suggests that shareholders can concentrate control without cash flow rights, creating incentives to expropriate firm resources. However, previous research does not help identify the board structure of firms whose controlling shareholder has an inflated control concentration. We investigate whether and how firm control concentration affects the structure of the board of directors. Building upon the literature on busy boards, we investigate specific characteristics of the board of directors: the number of directors’ directorships and the number of committee positions. We study an initial sample of 8688 firms from 41 countries. After using propensity score matching to mitigate selection bias, we keep 3570 firms. We find that controlling shareholders with higher control concentration select board members with more directorships and fewer committee positions. We interpret this result as evidence supporting the signaling incentive hypothesis, which suggests that controlling shareholders prefer a more shareholder-friendly board structure, possibly to signal the market that they pursue decisions that maximize firm value. The results are robust to several alternative specifications and methods. Our study helps fill gaps in the literature on busy boards by showing the consequences of the incentives of shareholders with concentrated control on how firms allocate the time of their busy directors. Our study also sheds light on the theoretical aspects that affect the preferences of those shareholders who can most harm minority shareholders. Finally, our study has practical implications that could help regulatory institutions make recommendations for the compositions of boards of directors and/or committees.</p>
<p>Co-authored with <a href="http://lattes.cnpq.br/7188849602769313">Cristiano Machado Costa</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Governance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/JMG_2020/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/JMG_2020/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Do shareholder protection and creditor rights have distinct effects on the association between debt maturity and ownership structure?</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/JBFA_2020/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.1111%2Fjbfa.12430" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">Do shareholder protection and creditor rights have distinct effects on the association between debt maturity and ownership structure?</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract"><em>Abstract:</em></h3>
<p>This study examines the effects of the firm’s ownership concentration and its institutional environment on corporate debt maturity choices. As ownership concentration and debt maturity are alternative governance mechanisms, we theorize and investigate whether their association is influenced by country-level governance factors that enhance outside monitoring by minority shareholders and debtholders. Our investigation is based on a dataset of 50,599 firm-year observations from 38 countries. We use a propensity-score matching approach and find that the effect of ownership concentration on debt maturity is conditional to country-level governance attributes. Ownership concentration has a negative effect on debt maturity in countries where both shareholder protection and creditor rights are weak. Ownership concentration, however, tends to lengthen debt maturity as protection increases, and this positive effect on the length of debt maturity is stronger in countries enhancing protection towards debtholders (instead of shareholders). We also explore other characteristics of ownership structure, such as the identity and presence of controlling shareholders. These results corroborate the view that entrenched shareholders may use debt maturity opportunistically. Our study provides new insights into the interplay between firm- and country-level governance mechanisms and a deeper understanding of cross-country differences in the association between ownership structure and debt financing.</p>
<p>Co-authored with <a href="https://www.hec.ca/en/profs/eduardo.schiehll.html">Eduardo Schiehll</a> and <a href="https://eaesp.fgv.br/en/people/paulo-renato-soares-terra">Paulo Terra</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Governance</category>
  <category>Corporate Finance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/JBFA_2020/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/JBFA_2020/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Brazilian bankruptcy law reform, corporate ownership concentration, and risk-taking</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/MDE_2020/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.1002%2Fmde.3120" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">The Brazilian bankruptcy law reform, corporate ownership concentration, and risk-taking</a></p>
<section id="abstract" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract"><em>Abstract:</em></h3>
<p>We investigate whether a bankruptcy reform, which increased creditors’ protection, affected the risk taking of Brazilian firms. Collecting data from Brazilian (treatment group) and Argentinian, Chilean, Colombian, Mexican, and Peruvian firms (control group) and using a difference-in-difference technique, we show that Brazilian firms with concentrated ownership structure decreased risk taking after the reform. Our results suggest that these firms reduced risk in response to increasing creditors’ protection, possibly because controlling shareholder fear losing control. Moreover, our results indicate that the reform probably provoked a wealth transfer from minorities to controlling shareholders.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Finance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/MDE_2020/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/MDE_2020/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Investor protection, managerial entrenchment, and cash holdings - Cross-country evidence</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/IF_2019/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.1111%2Finfi.12343" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">Investor protection, managerial entrenchment, and cash holdings: Cross-country evidence</a></p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em></p>
<p>We investigate whether investor protection (i.e.&nbsp;shareholder protection and creditor rights) is associated with how entrenched managers set corporate cash holdings. Our sample covers more than 6,000 firms from 29 countries (roughly 16,000 observations during 2010-2013). We find that the entrenchment-cash holdings association is sensitive to the level of shareholder protection but not to the level of creditor rights. Moreover, we find that the way shareholder protection shapes this association depends upon how managers become entrenched. When managers become entrenched through ownership, shareholders consent to their preferences to hold more cash, whereas, when managers become entrenched through CEO duality, shareholders force them to disgorge cash. We interpret our findings as evidence that shareholders agree to increase cash when managers are aligned with them by ownership but prefer to decrease cash when they are not aligned, whereas creditors do not influence entrenched managers’ cash holdings decisions.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Governance</category>
  <category>Corporate Finance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/IF_2019/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 02:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/IF_2019/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Country-level governance quality, ownership concentration, and debt maturity - A comparative study of Brazil and Chile</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/CGIR_2017/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.1111%2Fcorg.12192" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">Country-level governance quality, ownership concentration, and debt maturity: A comparative study of Brazil and Chile</a></p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<section id="research-questionissue" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="research-questionissue"><em>Research Question/Issue:</em></h3>
<p>This study investigates the interplay between country-level governance quality and the capital structure choice at the firm level in Brazil and Chile. We examine the association between a firm’s ownership concentration and its debt maturity structure and whether country-level governance quality influences this association.</p>
</section>
<section id="research-findingsresults" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="research-findingsresults"><em>Research Findings/Results:</em></h3>
<p>Using a large firm-level dataset from Brazil and Chile for the period 2008-2013, we find a positive association between low ownership concentration and debt maturity. However, this association becomes negative when the largest shareholder has high ownership concentration. This result suggests that long-term debt and ownership concentration act as substitute monitoring mechanisms. Moreover, debt maturity is inversely related to our aggregated index of country-level governance quality, suggesting that in countries with governance systems that effectively protect debt holders, firms with high benefits of control (high ownership concentration) will use debt with shorter repayment periods in order to benefit from frequent monitoring by debt holders. Overall, our results support the view that financial markets tend to pressure firms with high benefits of control or greater agency conflict to make a tradeoff between the benefits of control and the cost and maturity structure of debt financing.</p>
</section>
<section id="theoretical-implications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="theoretical-implications"><em>Theoretical Implications:</em></h3>
<p>This study contributes to the research on comparative corporate governance and capital structure. We also respond to recent calls to bridge the gap between under- and over-socialized views of corporate governance by examining the interplay between firm- and country-level governance variables. Our findings suggest a substitution effect between monitoring by equity holders and by debt holders, and that country-level governance quality exerts a disciplinary influence over a firm’s choice of debt maturity structure.</p>
</section>
<section id="practitioner-implications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practitioner-implications"><em>Practitioner Implications:</em></h3>
<p>Investors seeking to enter emerging markets such as Brazil and Chile can benefit from considering national governance factors that enhance debt holders’ external monitoring effectiveness. Because our findings show the importance of considering and improving the quality of country-level governance, they are also useful for policy makers aiming to reform corporate governance practices in emerging markets.</p>
<p>Co-authored with <a href="https://www.hec.ca/en/profs/eduardo.schiehll.html">Eduardo Schiehll</a> and <a href="https://eaesp.fgv.br/en/people/paulo-renato-soares-terra">Paulo Terra</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Governance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/CGIR_2017/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 03:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/CGIR_2017/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cross-National Governance Research - A Systematic Review and Assessment</title>
  <link>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/CGIR_2016/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><a href="https://plu.mx/plum/a/?doi=10.1111%2Fcorg.12158" data-popup="right" data-size="large" class="plumx-plum-print-popup" data-site="plum" data-hide-when-empty="true">Cross-National Governance Research: A Systematic Review and Assessment</a></p>
<section id="research-questionissue" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="research-questionissue"><em>Research Question/Issue:</em></h3>
<p>Using a systematic literature review approach, we survey 192 cross-national comparative studies published in 23 scholarly journals in the fields of accounting, economics, finance, and management for the period 2003 to 2014. The purpose is to synthesize and appraise the extant empirical research on the interplay between country- and firm-level governance mechanisms and the effects on firm outcomes. Particular focus is placed on studies that examine firm economic performance.</p>
</section>
<section id="research-findingsresults" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="research-findingsresults"><em>Research Findings/Results:</em></h3>
<p>We identify and distinguish between two groups of cross-national governance studies. The first type compares macro, country-level outcomes and the second compares three different firm-level outcomes: economic performance, governance mechanisms, and strategic decisions. We compare the theoretical frameworks used and further analyze the country-level factors and firm-level governance attributes that have been combined to investigate their interplay and the effects on firm outcomes. We find substantial variation in the use and measurement of country-level factors as well as a variety of causal forms used to explain the combined effects of country- and firm-level governance mechanisms. This wide variability precludes comparison, and consequently prevents identifying consistent patterns of influence between country-level governance factors and firm-level governance mechanisms and/or performance. We identify research gaps and provide fruitful directions for future research on this topic.</p>
</section>
<section id="theoretical-implications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="theoretical-implications"><em>Theoretical Implications:</em></h3>
<p>The cross-national governance research has been guided mainly by an economic perspective focusing on international differences in the effectiveness of specific governance mechanisms. Few comparative studies have integrated an institutional perspective or examined the external forces that drive the diffusion and use of specific governance mechanisms. Such integrative framework would improve the understanding of cross-national differences in the salient dimensions of country-level governance factors and how they mediate the effectiveness of firm-level governance mechanisms.</p>
</section>
<section id="practitioner-implications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practitioner-implications"><em>Practitioner Implications:</em></h3>
<p>Our results reveal that firm- and country-level governance mechanisms have been interacted and combined, either to address various agency problems or to compensate for a weak national environment. This calls for regulators and investors to consider national governance factors when assessing firm-level governance practices.</p>
<p>Co-authored with <a href="https://www.hec.ca/en/profs/eduardo.schiehll.html">Eduardo Schiehll</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <category>Corporate Governance</category>
  <guid>https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/CGIR_2016/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2016 02:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://henriquemartins.net/research/research/CGIR_2016/featured.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
